and so so the last step of this in your
in your exploration once you I
identified that small list of companies
is to start making contact with the
company and I don't want people to
confuse what I'm talking this is not
soliciting a company for a job it's very
specifically not that I'm going to put
that out there right away uh this is not
for you to ask for a job right and this
is for you to get research from somebody
who actually has jobs like the one you
want to get that knows what to do there
so and when I say reach out to an
employer I'm not talking about cold
calling there's many many ways to do
that I want to talk about that today I
want to talk about that right now and
I'm going to use I'm going to start with
a story so when I some of you know I
started out with a Russian major and I
had to switch to technology um I knew
that I had to make a very immediate
change and so I was I did the exact same
thing that I'm talking about I there
were I I looked around I was like well
damn I'm not going to be able to work in
in Russia and I gotta I gota I gotta you
know crunch on this I love the internet
I like where it's going I think it's
going to be a big thing I like the
technology um I like coding I like
typing I like being in front of a
computer so I went through all that
whole process and I was like well what
kind of companies even exist uh for the
internet you know there you know there
was nothing that I could think of I
didn't know so I started you know going
through the Fone book I mean this is the
'90s there was no internet yet and I
started looking around for different
companies I'm like okay I mean you're
going to laugh but there was like a and
copy serve and what's this right here
there's this uh this this tele there's
this what what's this and so there's
teleport there was um another company
called X Mission which is still around
uh in Utah It's All City Utah like oh
hey look at that because I like the idea
of using I I had just figured out how to
use the Internet by dialing in you know
and and um believe me you can find a way
to this to your own situation I so I
loved it I love the idea of working for
a company that provided these internet
services I knew that was going to be the
future I wanted to be associated with
that so I called them I called them
straight up I called I called up
xmission and I asked to speak to the
engineering department I said I said
hello I am University student I'm
considering employment opportunities I'm
doing some research uh you know I'm
doing some career related research and
you know related to my education uh
about about you know what are the
technologies that I would you mind is
there somebody from the engineering
department would they mind speaking with
me for a few minutes and um I got they
they patched me through to the
engineering team and I got this is
something it's kind of kind of
interesting side um most people it's
it's like it's like the career day thing
you like when you have a dad or a mom
sit you know go up in front of the class
and talk about what they do a lot of
people if if they don't enjoy their even
if they don't enjoy their job they do
love talking about what they do some
don't some really don't but there most
people
when you get them talking about what it
is they do and you show genuine interest
they love talking about it and those
people are fantastic mentors by the way
because all they have to do is answer
questions like and so sure enough I got
patched through to this to this engineer
who loved his job oh my God he loved it
so much and he was telling me he was
like oh that's thank you so much I was
just really grateful to him for giving
me his time I was like you know I am
just I'm just trying to find my way and
I I just thought it would be cool to
work for a company like xmission please
understand I'm not applying here I'm not
trying to get a job I just I just am
trying to prepare myself and I asked him
this question and I want you to write
this down if if you're going to follow
my advice on this I want you to write
this question down I asked him the
question I said what one
skill if I learned one specific skill
one specific skill one specific Tech you
know thing that I could do one specific
SK if I could learn one specific skill
that would make it so that you had to
hire me what would it be and without
dropping a beat he answered learn Pearl
and if you know about the '90s and
you're there's a bunch of veterans are
laughing right now um because you know
Pearl's an old technology but at the
time I the codebase that I am
immediately right now I'm I'm very
gainfully employed migrating an 80,000
line Pearl code base over to go and and
other things so I mean you know it was
definitely the right technology for the
time was he influenced by his own biases
yes he definitely was you know some and
he might have told me learn Arch today
or something right but and it would have
been wrong but the point is that this
person who was employed doing the kind
of job I like tell me what your jobs are
what what are the what is the name
what's your title what is the titles of
the people in your organization and I
was taking mad notes like writing down
all these cool things that he was
telling me about his job and he he was
loving talking to me about it and he
probably walked away from the
conversation thinking God I just helped
somebody out and this this can happen it
doesn't have to be you cold calling a
company this can also happen another
person I met influx DB influx DB I met
one of the cheap engineers at influx DB
at a Linux Meetup and we were you know
shooting the breeze and talking about
their opportunities and I was just so
curious I was asking them and I actually
brought some of my people that some a
couple of them ended up getting one of
them ended up getting a job there and a
lot of them all of them were being
considered but one of them actually got
the job and then you know they would
talk would talk with each other and
they' ask questions because it was a
Meetup scenario so and that it was like
informal mentoring the point is I wasn't
talking to some official company
representative I was talking to somebody
who was working in the job that I met
through a
Meetup about the job well what is it
that you do why are you coding this are
you coding and go or rust or see what's
going on with that what are the things
and people would ask the questions what
is the target programming language that
you're hiring for what is you know and
so and you know notes notes notes notes
this was not this was not officially a
solicitation for
employment which takes the pressure off
of the person that you're talking to if
if you are pushing for a job from the
very
beginning but if you tell them right at
the beginning look I just want to
understand the positions in your
organization because I want to prepare
myself to have a job for you and I
actually use this as a mentor as well I
called several cold called several
companies tech companies in the area one
of whom I won't name but but my one of
our guys got solar energy uh python
developer job uh there and I called them
I said look I've got people I've been
I'm helping to Mentor people prepare
this you know the beginning upcoming
Tech Workforce what do you need today
what is the number one thing the number
one skill that you are missing today
that you need give me you know the top
three give me the top one and the top
three and I said we need B I said said
what if I told you I had somebody who
could do that right now would you want
to would you want to talk to them and
that was me as a mentor and they say
absolutely and they talked to him and
they had just gotten they had just
gotten a grocery clerk job and they quit
that job and they ended up becoming a
python programmer at 16 for a solar
energy company which one would you
rather have on your ra of
me so this is this is a I I'm talking a
lot about this one because the act of
making contact with a potential employer
is scary that's the thing that people
freak out about they go oh my God I'm
going to you know I don't I they're
going to think I'm stupid and blah blah
blah but if you go in there telling them
that you don't know anything and that
you want to know more and then if they
they may come back they may come back
after the fact and they say I remember
you were saying that you were interested
in learning that you know and and you
know do you mind me you know keeping do
you ever raise me like no I'm not ready
yet you know but later on you might run
into you might you might have created a
bridge there for later and so you know
you go learn in 21 days or whatever I
never got a job for xmission but you
know what I did do within 3 months I got
a job for teleport internet services
which was five times as big as xmission
in Utah doing Pearl programming
specifically and when they hired me they
apologized that they couldn't pay me
$30,000
more and I had already doubled my income
from where I was
before because I went to another
internet service provider because I knew
that was the the thing I wanted to work
for and then I knew that's where the
jobs were and I had talked with an
internet service provider in the
engineering department in their
Development Department about the
potential jobs I had followed their
advice bought Pearl in 21 days just
crammed that and learned myself wrote
wrote a whole bunch of programs I wrote
a a mail merge program because I thought
it was cool and and then I used that and
when I when I applied when I applied to
the other job they apologized for not
being able to pay me more money and I
had just learned Pearl like within three
months they didn't care they didn't care
how I knew it they were like oh my God
we found a pearl
programmer now look I know that's silly
with the Pearl thing but I just want you
to know that that is how you get a job
that's how you prepare for a job that's
how you you know make these the
associations that you're going to get
and it's how you start to identify what
you're going to do and as soon as you
start to do that then the the questions
of self-doubt and Direction and not
knowing what you want to do or where you
want to go they start to fade away and
now you become really really focused
because now you not only have you you
know kind of done the exercise to figure
out what it is you want and everything
you've identifi potential employers
you've talked with specific people doing
similar jobs to what you want to do who
are encouraging you and then you also
got the plan from them a very specific
plan about one specific skill or two
that are going to make you completely
indispensable to the company and then
you focus on that thing focus on that
thing the other stuff that we do in the
Boost is kind of supportive for that one
thing whatever it is and then that one
thing is the thing you you leverage you
get the job boom and you're in and then
you can you can go from there you can
you can be the person that helps the
other person decide what they want to do
next um so the the rest of the videos
here are going to be how to you know
research uh job opportunities and things
like that